<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Royalist reform'd or Considerations of advice, to gentlemen, divines, lawyers. Digested into three chapters. VVherein their former mistakes are examined, and their duties of obedience, unto the present authority, succinctly held forth as rationall, and necessary. / By Albertus Warren, Gent.</title>
            <author>Warren, Albertus.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 105 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A97210</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W954</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E582_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204579</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864052</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864052</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116271</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A97210)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116271)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 89:E582[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Royalist reform'd or Considerations of advice, to gentlemen, divines, lawyers. Digested into three chapters. VVherein their former mistakes are examined, and their duties of obedience, unto the present authority, succinctly held forth as rationall, and necessary. / By Albertus Warren, Gent.</title>
                  <author>Warren, Albertus.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 44 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Francis Leach for George Thompson, dweling right against Lincolnes-Inne in Chancery Lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650. [i.e. 1649]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The words "gentlemen, .. lawyers." are bracketed together on title page.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nou 26 1649".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Royalists --  England --  History --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Common law --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116271:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ROYALIST <hi>REFORM'D</hi> Or Conſiderations of Advice,
<list>
                  <item>To <hi>Gentlemen,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>To <hi>Divines,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>To <hi>Lawyers.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> Digeſted into three Chapters. Wherein their former miſtakes are examined, and their duties of obedience, unto the preſent Authority, ſuccinctly held forth as rationall, and neceſſary.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Proverbs CHAP. 27. Verſe 6.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Faithfull are the wounds of a Friend: But the kiſſes of an Enemy are deceitfull.</p>
            </q>
            <p>By <hi>Albertus Warren,</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Francis Leach</hi> for <hi>George Thompſon,</hi> dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing right againſt Lincolnes-Inne in <hi>Chancery Lane.</hi> 1650.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:116271:2"/>
            <head>Ad Lectorem candidum, de Serie et uſu LIBELLI.</head>
            <l>DIſſingens regulas generoſis, ſponte Libello,</l>
            <l>pacis adeſt noſtro tempere, Cauſidicus.</l>
            <l>Dira Malignantis recolens molimina Cleri,</l>
            <l>Pneuma Sacroſanctum stringere fraude pia.</l>
            <l>Sphalmata Doctrinae legum ſubrepta notavit,</l>
            <l>ſic leges pateat DOSE carere ſua.</l>
            <l>Invicto <hi>ALBERTVS</hi> rationis flvmine victus,</l>
            <l>dux tibi ſub rabido ſidere (lector) erit.</l>
            <l>Ergo inter quondam tollentes regna Monarchae,</l>
            <l>ingenuo velox huic referatur honos.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:116271:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the</hi> Judicious Reader.</head>
            <p>BEing my ſelfe a free, unmercenary agent, how diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable ſoever (unto ſome men ſpringie braynes) my diſcourſe may appear, J paſſe not: becauſe, wiſer heads wil report me juſt in not ſmothering light upon te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of Relations, or prejudice. If to honor my prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors from Forreyne and Domestick tyranny be a ſuine, I ſhall offend till my death without regreat, the Crime wanting a name: we ſee the Governing part of our Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valry may challenge that reſpect as due, they being a People deſigned to great tranſactions; But how farre the ſympathy, and antipathy of ſounds diſtracts many eares we daily find; <hi>A</hi> reſtleſs Generation, undervaluing preſent felicities, rayſeth a Duſt in our eyes; But wiſe Mens diſcretion will either cloſe their ſights at its ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, or fanne it away. What ſhall we ſay unto Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians unpardonable folly, in coveting a regard (when formerly diſowned by now expir'd Regency) from their Church-Governments naturall Enemy? What to Roya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts Dreams after Materialls, which Heaven hath ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly declared unfit, and given many judicious verdicts againſt them? The firſt are only angry they mist the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb facs="tcp:116271:3"/>in not cutting of that head, which they themſelves had long before fitted unto the block, the ſecond vainly would indent with God which way they ſhall goe to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and both theſe raſhly weigh moſt perſons above us, in a Carnal ſcale, both are acceſsary unto the need leſſe arraignments of their own indiſcretions. Emulation and and preſumption wil diſparadiſe whom they captivate: God hath ſet a period to every forme, upon whoſe providence, who prudently depends, hath pitcht upon an Object, ſhall never taint his imagination. Let private intereſts, or diſaffected relations throw what ſcorn they can upon the ſeeming weaknes or audacity of my reaſon, ſhe ſhall never faile to concenter, and triumph in her high, undoubted, <hi>Divine parentage.</hi>
            </p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Non haec ſine numine Divûm eveniunt.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <!-- Virg Aen 2.777 ["devum"] -->
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>page 33 read diffutit for <hi>diſſit,</hi> Line 34 <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> for <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Pag. 38 line 9, read <hi>of</hi> for <hi>a.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:116271:3"/>
               <head>CHAP. I Reſpecting Gentlemen</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have been as much beholding either to ancient riches, learning, valor, or the like uncertain ſeed of Heraldry, as moſt men. &amp; am thereby obliged to a ſpecial regard of gentlemen; and gentries reputation: your exception (Gent.) is the leſs againſt me, yet I know neither birth, field valour, Eccleſiaſtick imployments, profeſſion in the Municipiall lawes of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> either in a Theoretick or practicall way, are ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to maintain a ſtock of vertue and diſcretion, but the variety of theſe qualifications forces me (who have little logicall art) to uſe ſome rude Method in my intended re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections, in order to each reſpective qualification I deale withall, beginning with thoſe who ſtand ſo much upon their right of reſpect by extraction or birth.</p>
               <p>Vnto ſuch it is not denyed, but that the vertue of their Anceſtors hath of due cut out great reſpect, yet ſuch is that regard, as muſt take its collaterall prop alſo up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and from ſecondary endowments, adding luſtie to the remote cauſe; and whereof your ſelves (Gent.) muſt be propper Maſters; otherwiſe empty pretenſions of bloud-worthineſs are idle, and indeed render the pretenders ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous, if not more conſpicuouſly ſordid.</p>
               <p>No Rant of breeding, as by moſt underſtood and confy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, either to a good pronuntiation of ſome forrein tonges behaviour with ladyes, poſtures artificiall of defence or the like (moſt uſeſull for all Gent. in due place) can with me be ever able to cancell the generall prejudice taken up againſt you, for doting to much upon thoſe external garbs
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:116271:4"/>and modes, while yet, the ſtudy of circumſtances, of men and times is ſo far neglected by you: while no diſcreet and religious obſerving ſurvey is made of Gods extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary actings in theſe dayes, neither of the height of Agents and Patients by Strange (to us) counterworkings.</p>
               <p>Many of you mark not the riſing and falls of men, Popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, Worldly, Wiſe, ayming at a Reformation of their owne, others at Gods, yet miſerably in the purſuit thereof, clog'd with Carnall paſſionate Intereſts.</p>
               <p>But I deſcerne many reaſons (as they ſeeme) deterring you from making a ſevere diſquiſition of contingences (whoſe neglect is follye's Nurſe) and theſe are only ſpecious gloſſes, partly colourd, and ſet out by rigid Epiſcopall men, partly upon feares of I know not what loſſe of <hi>Honor and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect</hi> are they begotten; but much upon an hurtfull fancy (grounded yet upon that Epiſcopall Anvill) of the indiſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible neceſſity of Monarchy, which many fooliſhly deny to have been at all qualified (but by meere grace of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch) in this or any other Nation, looking into the <hi>Iuda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ick Hiſtory</hi> (undeſigneable to ours, or any peoples regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but the Jewes) for all ſuch ſtrained Maximes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they moſt vainly abuſe themſelves and you. The wiſdome of this age hath ſufficiently to intelligent men, held forth the fallacie of thoſe impertinent diſputes.</p>
               <p>That there hath been, ever will be, in all ages, ſeverall ſpecifick notions of rule, in every Kingdome almoſt, ſeveral ſorts of Governours, is evident, by conceſſions of all Hyſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries ſacred, and prophane, this to make good, neither mood or figure wanteth.</p>
               <p>Who, without high preſumption dares aske why God (for ſecret reaſons in his counſell) hath ſuffered heere a tranſlation of legiſlative ſupreme power into new hands? this is in men, language, <hi>Alternacye</hi> of <hi>Providence</hi> in Divine Speech; It is his pleaſure.</p>
               <p>It is, in my judgement, a notorious peece of Foolery for any man to aske, by what right of Iuſtice the <hi>Hollander</hi> ſhak't of their Vſurper moſt fortunatly; his preſent quiet
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:116271:4"/>excerciſe of Religion, Peace, Riches, and all earthly happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe anſwers it.</p>
               <p>The Gent. of <hi>England</hi> looſe themſelves in being too credulouſly concluded by other mens Doctrines; Examples teach better then cold Logick, Perſons now a dayes are moſt to be ſtedied.</p>
               <p>Divide this Kingdome with your Eyes, and the Spawne of diſtracting Intereſt, either in Court, or Church, will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to have had to great an influence in generating Gentlemens extremities. In my retired thoughts, I have often admired, this Nation could ſo long endure the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible miſchiefes, that little (now headleſſe) Biſhop) by holding the Heart, and Eare of a King over us, brought to paſſe: his Beagles are good at cold hunting, but my advice unto you all is, (tendring herein your morall and Religious ſafety) that hereafter you do manage your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, and Intereſts (planted by God) like men and Gentlemen, that you do more narrowly look into their deſignes, who have thus captivated your underſtandings; ſee whether they and others, do not drive on their intereſts againſt God's deſigne, and how unhappily they have inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged many of you into deſperate attempts, loſſe of Eſtates, Priviledges, Freedome &amp;c. nay and many times driving on the torrent of youthfull heat, into an unreaſonable willfull pertinacie in apparent impoſſibilities, ever ſince this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſat. I wiſh it were not ſo. But I perceive the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices thoſe Clergy creatures have to inſnare you are diverſe, as the manner of their contrivances, for every one will not be catch't with the ſame baite, there is amongſt them a deboyſt fort of men, not much learned, yet able enough, upon every emergencie, at a Taverre, to ſhew all that is in them, by a kinde of unprofitable eloquence, theſe ſpend their time and precious howers in compoſing premeditated ſcurrilous Poems, or at leaſt ſputter out (between Hawke and Buzzard) a few extemporary Satyricall Rymes upon the viſible Authoritie of the Nation, the tickling foolery of which, inviteth Gentlemen to begge a Copy, ſound in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:116271:5"/>their Fobbs by the next Officer at midnight, to their great hazard and diſquiet. If theſe black Coates be not Poeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, they are great Newes-Mongers, But it's ten to one, if one word they utter, among a thouſand, be true, for theſe Gentlemen muſt pay reckonings.</p>
               <p>I have often wondred at them, that they are ſo open in their diſcourſes, but upon ſeverer ſence, I finde the reaſon why they are not reſerved, is, that Gallants may (at their firſt compellation) underſtand their humours, who have nothing to looſe, and they had rather goe ſlinking up and downe <hi>London</hi> in thredbare Coates, glorying in their ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings forſooth, then (temperately giving way to the premiſſive providence of Heaven in alteration of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment civill) teach a Schoole, or upon a new ſcore, goe Preach Gods Word, remitting State matters and Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techtonick adminiſtrations to States men, their ordinary is a <hi>non entity,</hi> they are at liberty. Of their dividing privat tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulent heads, I wiſh honeſt Gentlemen to be ware, for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voydance of their poyſonous inſtillations, I would have it well weighed.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>That is not materiall to Salvation, what government Civill a man lives under.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>That it is not yet diſcovered, what Church govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is of Divine right.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>That heroicall vertues are further'd mere (not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derd) under a Democraticall Government then under a Monarchicall.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>There is no need why I ſhould (others have ſaid ſo fully already) make a candid expoſure of the undoubted truth of the two former aſſertions. But the conſideration of the latter third poſition: <hi>viz.</hi> That Heroical vertues will thrive, and may be exerciſ'd better in a Democraticall, then a Monarchicall diſpenſation, will in a Domeſtick way be pertinent, towards the leading you out of that erroneus ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition mentioned before, among the cauſes of the the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrence, and keeping ſo great a diſtance from ſearching into the reaſon of things, and preſent condiſcention to Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:116271:5"/>
                  <hi>ſcilicet.</hi> That fear of Honors loſſe from that cauſe, leſſe doubt, I ſay, deterring Gentlemen from ſuffering qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly (as Heavens pleaſure) the immediate tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Publique truſt, not in their Powers to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void,</p>
               <p>If it delight your ſpirits to pry into ſuch rudiments, either of Theology, or Law <hi>Municipall,</hi> of this Kingdome, as lead Men inſtrumentally to honours, and places of truſt in this Kingdome; It will appear in reaſon, that men under a Democratick or Sanatory rule, ſhall not, will not be wholly at the Devotion of a Prince, or Tyrant, capacitated or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powred to throw them down cauſeleſſely from their deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved honourable truſt at pleaſure, ſo that in ſuch places of publick imployment, men may (under Democracy) do ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice more boldly, and diſcover to the world, upon every opportunity, their gifts of vnawed nature (not inſiſting upon though very conſiderable) that under <hi>Democracy</hi> or State-government, offices publick will not in probabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty be often referred to Deputies, as they uſually have been, partly by reaſon of hability preſumed for the future to be in future Officers, they being eligible by deſert, not Aulicall favour, and eſpecially regarding how all things will (as in their carriages of ſuch places) be laid forth, and ſubjected to general and publique queſtion, when as a fixt, ſtanding po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer for appeales, in caſes of injuſtice, wil be exiſtent, for puniſhing offences ſtarting up, for which no law was, or could be written: a great defect in Monarchie it was, where Lawes, reſpecting general equity ſuffered damnable miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs in particular.</p>
               <p>What therefore can be greater, or more pregnant incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to a Religious, active noble mind, then to breath in ſuch a Common wealth, (may ours prove ſo) where a Gappe is not only ſet open, for every ingenuous ſpirit, by Vertues ſtairs, to climbe up Honors Temple; but alſo a contrivance laid, that Envy, malice, ambition, covetouſnes, or the like, ſhall notably be ſtated of, in a Prudentiall way, from tumbling him down from thoſe ſweet turrets of repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:116271:6"/>and truſt; unleſſe thoſe Cardinall Vices, or their friends, be able firſt to bring in all the Studds, and groundcels of the Manſion or Manor houſe, (which muſt be rare) joyntly together, or the major part of them, into a conſpiracy againſt vertue, a conjunction of difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that muſt needs be, and very unfortunate; for doubtleſſe, a Community (as hath been often intimated) cannot be ſo eaſily miſled, neither ſo frequently defect from diſcretion, as the private Judgment or paſſion, of one individuall Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mericall perſon.</p>
               <p>Thus farre I have already endeavoured ſuccinctly a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>occupation of your preiudice. (Fellow Gentlemen) who mind ſomething higher then an horſe, or dogge, your mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes, or recreation at Tennis or a Bowling alley; for it is your good I principally intend hereby. Give me leave be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I paſſe any further, to take a lttle pitty on ſuch others (whoſe heads are Synechdochcially ſoft) for quietneſſe ſake, for they are affraid high ſhoe's will ſit above them, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I referre (with reverence) alſo unto the underſtanding conteurplative Gent. (then whom I have none more hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py in this world) In order whereunto, as to a poſſibility or probability of extenuating that reſpect and honor, (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with born Gent. are already inveſted) under a State-govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (if Heaven will have it ſo) it is not greatly to be ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected in reaſon; For as moſt men either are gentlemen or would be ſo, and one main reaſon, as may be ſuppoſed, why the Lineall gentlemen (not of the firſt, ſecond, or third head (theſe are things much look't into by many I promiſe you) but of a long ſeries in Herauldry, were no better eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in Regal times, was, becauſe Honor lay then radical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Kings of this Nation, it dwelt in their naturall, not Politique capacity, yet was it ſo corruptly ſhed in hands of ſubordinate Officers, for diſpenſation of it, that any man might be made a gentleman for money, mony would make a man a Knight though no gentleman; but if a Parliament be the ſupreme Judicatory of the Nation, though as you ſee now abſtracted from Kings, actually impowred heretofore
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:116271:6"/>by a King; If I ſay you grant or but admit them (as who can deny that) Nomotheticall at preſent, queſtionleſſe, they are capacitated to give, and create honours, aſ well as laws, they may and will grant honors, defer rewards for ſervices Civil and Martiall; And in all likelyhood, they will be pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in foreſeeing, That as acceſſions of honor, or creation thereof, are great incentives to gallant Spirits, towards he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roicall Vertues; ſo the too to frequent collation of titles, will render honor leſſe deſirable, leſſe eſteemed. Upon which it muſt neceſſarily follow, that ancient gentlemens honours, being already their own, and other mens acquira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble only upon ſuch extraordinary preſumptions, the latter will not exceedingly multiply, their Lineall ſplendor will ſhine more uncontroulably, without numerous Rivalry, or Competition,</p>
               <p>And without queſtion, in ſuch governments, where pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerments will be gainable by deſert (preſuming it for the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſo in our State) Learning is like enough to flouriſh, (though ſom lazie functions and vaſt miſimployed proventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons be diſſipated) for as much as this obſtruction will be canceld.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quorum virtutibus obſtat res auguſta Domi,</hi> when to be borne of honeſt, but poore Parents, ſhall not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure thoſe excellencies (under a Cottage, better beſeeming a Court) beſtowed by the God of. Nature not in vaine, when money, or favor of freinds ſhall not wholly prevaile, for inveſting in places of truſt undeſerving men, where, vertue ſhall not wait upon perſons. (<hi>The bane of all States</hi>) which indeed was our caſe under Regal government, where, prerogatives, priviledges, and exemptions ſhall not nurſe up in juſtice or Tyranny. Learning will encreaſe in ſuch a Kingdome, where, a man may get a fortune by his learning, ſooner then by his friends, Priviledges and exemptions are not friends, but Enemies to the Muſes, let men be what Schollers they will, without judgement, they are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit for the Miniſtry, or the State. Nothing is more hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to a free People then particular exemptions from ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:116271:7"/>Lawes, then Royall or Subject prerogatives, then Regall <hi>non obſtantes,</hi> reſerved in grants formerly, but the preſent viſible Authority hath well curtayl'd thoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences in their extention, by ſubjecting all men generally to Law, none of the leaſt happineſſes to a Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I aſſure you. But I return to my diſcoveries premiſed, and the inſtant hinderances of Gentlemens abhorrence from dutie that Jealouſie of Honors loſſe, being remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and the contrary cleared conſeqnently, as I hope in naturall reaſon.</p>
               <p>There ſtarts up next, a ſecond ſort of Eccleſiaſtiacall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who pretend to know much, mightily oppugning your condiſcention to Authority, and ſubſcription to that power, under which God hath plac't us all, they are Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biterian Divines, that will hand over head, have ſuch formes of externall diſcipline, and impulſions upon ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der conſciences fixt, or elſe endeavour they will, a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of all civill ſociety and corporate ſtrength of this Nation, by talking up, and elevating their humane in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions under Seraphick notions of Chriſts government, theſe will not ſuffer you like wary wiſe men, to ſit under your owne Vines, ſleep in whole skinnes, while Martiall men trye the quarrell, I feare they drive on an Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall deſigne (though pretenders to a pious Reformation) beware of them, at preſent, let it ſuffice, they are no fit adviſers of you unto whom afterwards alſo in a more ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable and methodicall place, I ſhall more fully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate their dutie!</p>
               <p>Amongſt other cauſes of gentlemens unhapy pertinacy, and ſtubborneſſe, I find, <hi>That a conceipt of a certein New ſin called falling or defection from Principles,</hi> carryed forth in diſcourſe by Parſons, and made fellowes, from one Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern to another, mainly hinders their condiſcention, and as conſcious of ſuch appoſtacy, I have by ignorant preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders been often taxed; the meaning is, that becauſe a man was once wedg'd up with an implicite faith, belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving what ſome grave hobby horſes ſaid, <hi>viz,</hi> a King is
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:116271:7"/>above all Law; Biſhops are of divine inſtitution, The Lawes of <hi>England</hi> are ſo exact, as they need no Reformation &amp;c. I may not forſooth upon more light intervention of better rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, conviction of conſcience or judgment, unhalter my ſelf (ſo likewiſe others) from thoſe paradoxes, for fear of being ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected to the ſcandall of falling from principles. This hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor of perſeverance in miſguided reaſon, is ſo ridiculous, and yet withall ſo prevalent, in the ſoft braines of ſome Gent. that I have admir'd to heare it objected, much leſſe brought forth as Categoricall, in ſetling vain conſtancy; becauſe once a fool therefore ever a fool.</p>
               <p>Neither am I ignorant that many of you of good capacity and tempers, are extreamly culpable, upon another ground, though ſeemingly more politick, yet indeed altogether as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable in Chriſtian conſideration, you will not ſtoop one tittle unto thoſe mighty reflections of Scripture, and reaſon commanding you (under payn of being accounted worthily ſome of <hi>Paul's</hi> infidels, in not providing for your families in things indifferent) to concurre.</p>
               <p>Gentlemen bluſter at Authorities indictions, diſcover their diſſafections, drink healths, making themſelves lyable to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Tapſters and Chamberlains malice, ſometimes againſt their own ſence; ſay as the Companie ſaith, abundantly fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in all things; leaſt the world ſhould occaſionally think, they are fallen from principles. And why is all this tepid foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery in theſe wiſer ones, think you? it is, for that having once maintained ſuch or ſuch a tenet, it being notorious they were of ſuch a Faith, they will not be ſo ingenuous, as to confeſſe an errour as men. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> was of another mind in his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractions; and, had they bin ſo religiously politique, their Fynes happily had been more favourable. <hi>I</hi> perſwade no man againſt his Conſcience; but I ſay, unreaſonable ſtubborn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in matters of a midling indifferent nature, is no ſymp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of valour; or magnanimity Fitting a Gentlemans bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
               <p>I have ever found old Grand Iury men (generally by country people ſuppoſed to know much very unfit to judge or direct a mans comportment, in theſe troubleſome times, for as the old
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:116271:8"/>ſaying is, wiſe at fifty or never, they being only knowing in ſuch tranſactious as concerned Indictments, and the like County affaires, and many of them ſuppoſing Lawes are ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credly upon the matter unalterable, neither that their influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence may be ſuſpended, upon ſome exigence, where <hi>Salus Populi</hi> comes in queſtion, yet the manner is, to flye unto their gray Beards as an Oracle for Counſell, when a new Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dnance of Parliament firſt appeares, wherein it cannot be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyded, but ſometimes, ſomething muſt be leſt to mens diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretions, and election of parties, here Grand lurors are at a ſtand, for the more any man is uſed to Formes, the leſſe is he able to judge of an Emergent.</p>
               <p>But above all others, meere Schollers would be avoyded by Gentlemen in point of conſultation of the times, for they are only skilled in Contemplation, and the chiefe books about governments, were written in old darke times when Tyrants were the only Kings, and doubtleſſe, people had not that vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacity of underſtanding what it is, to be envaſſeled unto deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poticall Arbitrary powers, in thoſe dayes, wherefore how is it likely, that Academick men, tuter'd up by ſuch Maſters as the Vniverſity afforded, (Apes only to thoſe books) whoſe intereſt, and dependancyes were linkt to the Royall Seat, and who were not preferrable, unleſſe of a temperament ready for aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerting of a Monarchicall and Epiſcopall governments, ſhould well direct you, I ſee not.</p>
               <p>No man alive honors Learning more then my ſelfe, though the tennity of my capacity be ſuch as can add no honor unto it. But temper and reaſon muſt guide the opinions of Ayrie termes, and Metaphyſick notions, otherwiſe, how miſchei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous they are, when falling upon eyther a vile, or towring Spirit, is ordinarily diſcerned, yet may it be lawfull to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, that Schoole learning poyſons ſome conſtitutions. God is judge of my candid ambition in theſe Papers; So far pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent I would have Gentlemen, as not in indifferent things, irrationally to ſtrive againſt the Bent of Heavens decree, leaſt by raſh and needleſſe extravagancies, you compell Authority unwillingly to make you get power, a thing truely I hope, not deſired by Authority. How much wiſer will it be for
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:116271:8"/>Gentlemen to keep their heads above water in theſe preſent currents, ſince we are in <hi>England</hi> yet (thanks be to God) bounded with Lawes, where a well compoſ'd man, may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy freedomes of conſcience, ayre books and recreations. And although you judgements be not wholly ſatisfied of the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullneſſe of ſomethings, yet let reaſon teach us all; that how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it happen, we are now in a moſt fair way for getting moſt wholeſome Lawes eſtabliſhed (though with alterations of ſome old ones) ſuch I ſay, as that, if God will afterwards in his high diſcretion introduce a priſtine forme of Government inſtead of the preſent exiſtent, thoſe after Ages will bluſh to abrogate, what ſo wholeſome by preſent Law-givers have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed.</p>
               <p>Neither let the fancies of thoſe men, who (too much affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, either with an over-weening apprehenſion of their owne skill or deſerts, or precipitantly carried on by a ſecret divine power, for houlding forth Gods work, er'ſt prime inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in thoſe actions wherein the Parliament hath ſo migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely prevailed) buſtled ſomewhat this Summer, but more dangerouſly the laſt before this, ſpeaking perhaps ſomewhat beyond themſelves in ſome particulars, (yet to wiſe to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour a parity in Civill Adminiſtrations) let not ſuch I ſay, befoole you into groundleſſe hopes nor cauſe yet in Gent. a further abhorrence from condiſcending to Superiors: for of this be aſſured, If you act as common enemies, let the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of ſuch impolitick drifts blaze when they will, that flame will beget a ſurer fixation and conjuncture againſt the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Enemy, and it ſhall prove a meere exhalation, but the matter of it, will light upon your heads.</p>
               <p>The main pretenſions of many now mingled, diſcontented and ignorant parties (beſide the old royaliſts) are in effect, theſe. <hi>ſcilicet, That the preſent Authority at</hi> Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>hath not done ſuch and ſuch acts, in purſuance of ſuch premiſed forms and modes of actings in civill matters, Qui judex eſt Rei judex eſt cauſae:</hi> their own conceſſions will ſtiffle their own arguments, which grant the parliament ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme, and of power to give Lawes, and definitive ſentence; what then if intentions in things purely morall, were premi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:116271:9"/>might not ſuch reaſon interveen, as might cauſe them (not to alter reſolutions perhaps) but <hi>de mado,</hi> to traverſe their own tempeſtive, and opportune votes, as tempeſtively, &amp; opportunely, as prudentially as providentially (cauſes chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) and with as great reaſon, to retract as art. Their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happineſſe lies only in this, that (enduring ſo great and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplicious cares) they cannot poſſibly preamble every vote, or art at large, this may excuſe them, ſince it muſt be granted by common indulgence, though few obſerve it, that the reaſon at large of few ſtatutes can be prefaced, unleſſe the preface or preamble, ſhould ſwell beyond the Law; like the gates of <hi>Mindus,</hi> wide enough for the City to run out of it,</p>
               <p>The neſcience, or at leaſt neglect of which knowledge; hath ſometimes it is probable, expoſed the houſes Declarations to unworthy ſcandalls, becauſe of the ſeeming diametricall oppoſitions in ſeverall ordinances of one indiction to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and yet theſe are not oppoſite ſences, nor contradictions in the adject, but an alternate effluxe of diſcretion in emer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencies of neceſſity requiring ſuch refractive dociſion, adap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted both, upon rationall grounds; which alas is cleared unto us as lawfull in Domeſtick affairs, where alterings of reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons was never (but as it may be circumſtantiated) nakedly a ſin, or accounted ſo, and in truth can no more be imputed as declivitie from right reaſon (or underſtood as inconſtancy, then when a man ſhall ſay, he will ride to <hi>London</hi> ſuch a day (perfining unto himſelf his end in that journey) when in the mean time, by ſome intervening accident his end is atteyned, and journey to <hi>London</hi> ſtopt.</p>
               <p>Vpon this diſcretion of alterration all humane laws depend; this is now very remarkable to my apprehenſion not ſo before; but I the rather now confeſſe it, becauſe I think it moſt ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſo to do, and heartily wiſh you the ſame light, be not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to make recognition of extrication from errors as to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth.</p>
               <p>I am now (preſuppoſing your diſcretion (Gent) that there may be chang of governments in Kingdoms, and that there is no neceſſity of an identicall government) come to ſhew you ſome thing in reaſon, why I think, Monarchy will ceaſe here, adviſing ſtill obviouſly as occaſion happens.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:116271:9"/>
               <p>Before I come to that, the Pragmatick Lawyer will draw me aſide into admiration, who the better to bolſter up his <hi>Diana,</hi> ſays, that the Priviledges and Prerogatives of Kingly Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (which I know is alſo Gods Ordinance) is of indiſcenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble divine right, truly, no ſound Theologiſt but will acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge other formes alſo ſo to claim, but neither of them all of an indiſpenſible neceſſity, but the truth is, they of the Book law in this ſtate, have borrowed many ſhifts out of the Civill Law (to make good their aſſertions) uſed moſt what in times of abſolute regall, unlimmitted power; and inſenſibly put upon us by cowing out the peoples ſpirits, no leſſe by Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificiall then Monarchicall uſurpations, To the Lawyer we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to ſpeak apart.</p>
               <p>But that it is now verie probable Government by a King wil ceaſe in this Kingdome, upon ſerious conſideration of matters and things no temperate man will deny. I am none of thoſe, who build their confidence of it's ruine upon pretended prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, neither upon judiciall Aſtrology, but by the Star of humane reaſon, and by compariſon of paſt and preſent tranſactions; neer gueſſes are often made, yet I ſuppoſe [letting paſſe remote cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes] it will be worth while to conſider the infinite ſucceſſes on the Parliaments ſide, [for it is not ſo heatheniſh as ſome would have it, in all caſes to judge of matters by event] that percluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of cenſures by contingencies, muſt, as I take it be referred or underſtood with reflection to the fortune or accident, of ſome particular ſights, or ſinguler manageries of ſome few actions, by party againſt pary, as the Jewes againſt the Philiſtines; our caſe is otherwiſe, and not merely fortunable; for, we have for 7 or 8 years obſerved how all open force (upon equall congreſſes) pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate publique ſtratagems, and machinations, plots and contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances for morall advantages, carried on many times by perſons of extraordinary capacities (Heavens ayd being ſolemnly as in appearance pray'd) defections of Truſtees from the State, or whatſoever elſe tentations for re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ling the late King and his Intereſt, have been fruitleſſe, and, which is much, by how much more likely any thing was to take effect; God in its prevention and fruſtration (caſſating men's policies) in their height, hath then in ſuch nicks of Time, made bare his arme againſt it, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:116271:10"/>notably blaſted the managers of ſuch devices.</p>
               <p>It is confeſt the calmeſt of Gentlemen object not imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently, how all Hiſtories witneſſe, that God hath permitted wicked parties to do great matters againſt a better cauſe, ſlaves ſay you, have envaſſaled their Maſters, Rebells (ſuch is your language) have ſlid into Soveraignty: But I am confident no Hiſtory can paralell our times, obſerve the difference here, God hath ſuffered not one partie, not the ambition of one man, not ſometimes the prevailing indirect partie of our Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate body, to carry on his work; his Divine Majeſty hath often by ſtrange alterations done wonders, by thoſe, whom preſently againe he hath caſt of, diſcerning falſehood from truth rallying up publick ſpirits, when there was inhumane judgement, little hopes of ſuch helps, and in the cloſe, hath ſet up this new Modellizd army (thought very inconſiderable) which as a clowd hath obſcured, by its atcheivements, as wel Martiall as Civill, even I ſay, with a Curtaine of terror and obliv on hath darkned all former victories and actions, ſince this Parliaments firſt convention: whence it is evident (loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king well into things, and perſons now at the Sterne poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick and martiall, that they who in your apprehentions, long ago, did hatch theſe alterations are, if it were ſo, prevented of their deep and ſecret hopes, and this preſent ſupremacy, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons acting in it (in reſpective capacities) called to act but of late, in reſpect of ſuch old contrivers, could not orignally be guilty of ſuch ambitious deſignes; I am ſure ſmall hopes they had in their privat capacities of thoſe great honors, and truſt, whereunto providence hath now called them, and faſtened upon their ſholdiers.</p>
               <p>Neither the late Kings, great knowledge, errors or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunacy were obtruded upon theſe Kingdomes by accident, providence alſo would have it thus, and undone it cannot be, hee is a foole that wiſheth it.</p>
               <p>It is above me, to diſpute, what poor hopes his iſſue hath actually to were the Scepter of government here, yet I beleeve, the Spaniſh example in 88. will ſtartle many ſorreyners, when eſpecially they ſhall conſider our preſent poſture of defence, and offence. We might go backward, and ſee what the Pore
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:116271:10"/>(ſuppoſedly Chriſts Vicar) could doe to <hi>England,</hi> in <hi>H.</hi> 8. time upon our politick defection from him. I will not deny, but God may permit us againe to be governed by a King, but few examples can be produced of any people, having ſhak't of that government, over whom Regal intereſt could preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prevaile; that introduction of Kings upon the Romans, after expulſion of their Tyrants, was late, and after many a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. It is freſh in memory how Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> aſſiſted the <hi>Hollander</hi> againſt <hi>Spaine,</hi> a thing held lawful then, evince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereby that ſpecies of government are of a politick, not religious concernment, the mediocrity of Specifical modes of governing, is Analogicall, reſpecting times, perſons, and ſafety of Nations governed. However it is ſcarce poſſible for a King to be veſted with government here, without an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute conqueſt, and that by outlandiſh mercinaryes, our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition then muſt be bad enough, we ſhall pay full dearely for a King. When ſafety outweighs Danger, he is a foole that neglect it, when danger out weighes ſafety, he is ſilly that attempteth it.</p>
               <p>What ever Heaven will, muſt come to paſſe, leave theſe things to God, nothing of humane paſſion can hinder his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, therefore, come it to paſſe how it will (as to reſetling of priſtine intereſt or not, whereof there is ſo ſlender hope) better it is to be a Willow then an Oake. And for our meane car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, let us not ſo much examine other mens Religion as our owne, ſooner, or latter moſt of you muſt come to my humor of Reformation.</p>
               <p>But I perceive there is one thing ſtumbles many Barbatulous Ladds amongſt you, enough, many think, to foment diſaffecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and make any man a Malignant; And that is, a putting downe of Stage playes. Alter but the <hi>Scene,</hi> and many Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits will be as whimſically apiſh to your wild ſence; and for ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vearer Eires of Gentlemen, the <hi>Tragick Commedy</hi> of flaceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Tithes, ſupercilliouſly acted every ſeventh day by the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits-demiſed premiſes, terribly deploring the but neceſſary re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulating of them, is ſuper excellent: wherein leaſt you ſhould be wanting that have right of Preſentations, I have lately ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, how unable you are. O ſtrong Policy (upon all lapſes
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:116271:11"/>by Gods privation) in preferring a pontificall creature for feare the Reſpective Pariſhes ſhould petition for election of their Miniſter. A thing ſo reaſonable and juſt, as nothing can be more equitable.</p>
               <p>Thus we ſhew our teeth, &amp; cannot bite, foreſeeing not, how eaſily one lift of the Soldiery can ſcatter and diſmantle that weak ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creſcent <hi>Babel,</hi> no hard matter to be done, becauſe already, moſt Miniſters languages are different, and their doctrines like con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertible reſponds of an Oricle. Ceaſe then to wonder, why generaly, Ciergy men neigh after new quarrels, and combuſtions continually yelp and bark againſt Armyes, peace and ſettlement under preſent authority, ſince it is evdent, there is good cauſe for ſuch excurſions, aſwell regarding their double malice as poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, their malice againſt all not crediting their doctrines to be EVANGELICA<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>LL, (though never ſo carnal) their pollicies in begetting troubleſome matter for <hi>Ephemerides.</hi> or Journall Book, whoſe matter, dilated upon, is of great effieacy for ſpinning out diſcourſe, till the hour-glaſſe become as empty above of ſand as their Braines of true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
               <p>I beſeech you (Gentlemen) be not too much prejudiced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt private exerciſes in Religion, for Charityes ſake I will ſuppoſe though they (in your judgment) may miſſe in cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance, yet there is much of devotion in them. Churches, and houſes are alike in themſelves, but as they are circumſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated: And my conſcience forces me here to diſcover, how ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall the objection raiſed by ſome (no fooles) againſt the more Publick and ſolemn diſpenſations of Divinity in Churches, is, in my apprehenſion, <hi>viz. We cannot</hi> (ſay they) <hi>make anſwer in the Churches, to falſe Doctrine delivered, neither ſoberly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſie an erring ſpirit.</hi> Indeed this objection is ſubnixt with great reaſon, for it ſprings naturally from not leſſe care, for avoydance of diſturbation, then fervent zeale of Edificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>Neither are the maine reaſons of many mens averſeneſſe, and abhorrence from thoſe kinde of domeſtick duties obſcure unto mee, which are couchible under this fallacy, That Canonicall Doctors teach Truth, as it is truth, abſtracted, from degrees
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:116271:11"/>intenſive, in matters of Religion, is (ſay they) already ſo dogmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally laid down and made out, that beyond theſe, or theſe Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheticall or did acticall poſitions of Orthodox doctrines, there is no <hi>plus ultre.</hi> this was never denyed by me.</p>
               <p>But leave is craved to tell them, Orthodox is a very hard word of digeſtion, and that want they impoſe, as to a neceſsity of ſome neceſſary, ſtanding, fixt and perpetuall formall adminiſtrations, is often but mere deduction logicall from Allegorical ſcriptures, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of other conſtructions, beſide theirs.</p>
               <p>Wherefore inlightned Saints dare not otherwiſe beleive, but that God, in his infinite wiſedome, hath, and ever will reſerve (till the common annihilation of earth) many ſecret truths communicable in all ages, and that in a more tranſcendent way of light, then what hath been delivered apart <hi>ante,</hi> or (as Schollers ſay) from the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedent cauſe, otherwiſe to what purpoſe are thoſe commands in Scripture of ſearching, waiting, &amp;c. otherwiſe, we ſhould have nothing to do with ſpeculation in Divine matters; and we could have no other work then a common perſeverance up <hi>Iacobs</hi> lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der into Heaven.</p>
               <p>You are not to believe any tenet, becauſe ſuch men have ſaid ſo, a mans own diſcretion (from above originally) will be his beſt guide, in morall and Religious actions, modern Pulpit men will affirme, That moſt of the Fathers, celebrated for Orthodox Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lums in Chriſtianity, were but ſo orthodox in a favourable accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation: I beleive they were knowingly religious in thoſe times, yet far inferiour in knowledge to many men now a dayes, ſo as (not palliating any ſoul living) In truth I think, there is a poſſibility of atteyning an aetheriall bleſſed <hi>ubi</hi> through Chriſt, without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leiving all for neceſſary truths, which either Synods, or late Churchmen have laid down, as eſſentiall to my journey, to a place they know not where, and vainly labor to preſine circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptively.</p>
               <p>For your deportment in condiſcention to the formall outward Church and Officers in it, there is no more pendentiall way for rightly fixing you in a poſſure of indempnity, then in detecting unto your ſence, the indifferency of many things obtraded, as that of a baſon inſtead of a Font.</p>
               <p>A Gentleman is not mnch the worſe (keeping his Conſcience
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:116271:12"/>upright) though a Clergy man pronounce him Aheiſticall, meerely for that he will not reſt, either in fallible deciſions of any Synod, or inithe urgement of any Individuall Presbyter implicitely. Some ſay, it had been wiſer, and eaſier (reflecting to the erection of the Baſon in many Churches) by declaring the indifferency of ſuch circumſtantiated decencies as well to Papiſts as Proteſtants to have reteyned diſcontented men from Separation (as they terme it) then in theſe obſerving dayes by altering formes for forme, or adding forme to Formes, to generate a more quick diſcompoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt order externall, againſt goeing to materiall Churches, which is the moſt decent and convenient way.</p>
               <p>The beſt uſe can be made by warie knowing men, of that and other impoſitions like it, will be gatherec, by a rationall reference unto what I have ſaid or ſhall ſay in favour of the preſent Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and their diſcretion, religiouſly actuated in cancelling ſuch rigid Statutes, which to much tortur'd tender conſciences, upon pretences of Error, Hernſies, Schiſme &amp;c. for I have heard very religious and wiſe men affirme in their judgements, that the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe of many in the Parliament was over voted, when in many things prevalent voyces to gratefie the Synods importunity, ſilenced at preſent, others (that had not then liberty to enter diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents) of a contrary judgement.</p>
               <p>Although it hath often repented me for the foure pence ſpent in purchaſe of the <hi>Directory,</hi> yet, the honour put upon it by Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities approbation, made me very ambitious of it for peruſall. If you think there was no great worth in that <hi>Canon,</hi> keep it unto your ſelves, let that be (if an error) only the reſpective ſingle. lapſe of your underſtandings. A dangerous defection it is, for private perſons to condemne the Act of a Community.</p>
               <p>Nothing hath done Gentlemen more hurt then a vain reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt ſo much as reading over books; Ordinances and Votes of Parliament, only ſo feare they ſhould be infected (for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>footh) with errors (as ſome peeviſhly think) both in Church and State, how can men judge rightly, or behave themſelves tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratly avoyding Rocks and Shelves? If they will not by reading, obſerve the commands of Authority, the Bent of every party and Intereſt.</p>
               <p>If (all this notwithſtanding) any amongſt you, be perſwaded
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:116271:12"/>that Monarchy will reſettle here, and upon that improbable hope, will not compound, when as hitherto the indulgence of Parliament, and their unwillingneſſe to ruine you is evident, let me tell you, ſuch men are the greateſt Enemies to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, their Children and Families. I wiſh them wiſer, and that Gentlemen would read and obſerve all Ordinances which concerne generall goods, ſo may you know when to act, where to avoid, by reſpective condiſcention, concurrence, or giving way, unto the rapid torrent of theſe nimble dayes.</p>
               <p>On the other hand, ſuppoſing ſome glimering of light, and high reaſon in many of you, formerly more devoted to obſolet formes, ſhall prompt a Theoretick ſevere diſquiſition, or obſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vance what ſmall hope there is of reſetling former government; ſtick not to confeſſe it, that others may inſtrumentally add more ſparks thereto; leaſt you do utterly diſcupacit te your ſelves (by further vaine holding of) from places of truſt in the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth; leaſt inferior men of birth, and breeding ingroſſe all places of honourable civil command, and moſt Gentlemen for ever afterwards walke up and downe, like uſeleſſe Pageants.</p>
               <p>I am confident this advice of mine with the wiſeſt Gentlemen will be well taken, the rather, becauſe. I have ever ſince the firſt of this Parliament, lead a private life, never intermedling with profitable publike imployment which, it is well known I have been offered, not unbefitting a Gentleman (ſtill contenting my ſelfe with a diſcended competency) how how much I have ſaid, what I have hazarded upon the royall intereſt upon a principle of apprehended duty then, (not carried on implicitely upon the wings of others diſcretion) a way very unſutable to my temper ſo long as it pleaſed God to keep it upright in this Nation, yet all this without malice, to the honourable Houſe of Parliament. This by the way remembring, (becauſe it being cleared unto ſome examiners of my actions, that my ingagements were not altogether unſubnixt with a generall deſire of my Countries liberty, and quiet, and my reaſon was quadrated into a candid confeſſion upon what diſcretion: I had waded, upon what I would acquieſce; and not ſtrive againſt Heaven) I received in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite courteſies from the Army at <hi>Colcheſter</hi> Leaguer, and ſome knowing Gentlemen of <hi>Eſſex</hi> Committee, at a time, when I
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:116271:13"/>was juſtly repreſented as diſaffected, which lawfull favours chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge from my pen a gratefull commemoration.</p>
               <p>A yeare or two more (Gent.) will habituate the preſent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and then perhaps this councell will be thought good by moſt of you at inſtant, it is hoped, much prejudice may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved from theſe lines; for that this birth is ſpontaneous, free, voluntary, not brought forth by ſubtle midwiferv of other men, given by a quiet unſequeſtred hand, and moſt affectionate lover of his Native countries peace. Remember then who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend they had not thought, thank your ſelves if too late you cry <hi>out 'O Vtinam.</hi> I know your heart; are much ſick with expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion deferred, whoſe fruition (as is moſt clear) is not eſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntially neceſſary to your well being here, and which ought to be the greateſt comfort) God can ſave eternally under any outward po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litick diſpenſation. This Paper (let what will come to paſſe) will bear teſtimony of my good will towards my fellow gent. of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands Common wealth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sapientis eſt in conſilio, fortunam ſemper habere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>While the ſcales were equall; nay, while there appeared but a poſſibility of reſtoring a King, ſomething of reaſon and diſcreet principles, might create in loyall hearts (for not one in twenty in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged meerly upon loyalty) a deſire and flagrant fervency of act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and managing all ſeeming opportunities, towards that end.</p>
               <p>But for Men of any breeding, now in this ſtate of things, and pleaſure of heaven (not fortune merely for with a Chriſtian there is no ſuch thing as fortune) to talk themſelves into diſcapacity, contempt and miſery, for a man, that can neither help himſelf, nor his followers whoſe very intereſt (originally by conqueſt) is precluded actualy, whoſe title of guardianſhip, all men in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land confeſſe fiduciary, If ever it had been reduced to reall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſtiture, and could not, cannot much benifit privare perſons what ever ſome pleaſe to ſay, I ſay for Gent. or others ſtill to continue in Rebelion againſt reaſon, is a deſigne either of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, pride, or weak malice.</p>
               <p>Let it ſuffice we have not (as in a dreame) parted with Kingly Government, the world will believe our Nation is generally vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant, let it alſo underſtand we are rationall; the terrour of the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:116271:13"/>one, and notable contemplation of the other may probably ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle forrein enemies, from whoſe violence, who will not pray to be preſerved, for preventian of whoſe intollerable inſolencyes, who will not lay out his natural faculties and eſtate, deſerveth neithe: the title of a Gentleman or protection of a Subiect.</p>
               <p>Vpon the whole matter laſtly. Are we eitheir aware of thoſe unavoydable miſchiefs, another alteration of Government, uſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable in by forreigne powers muſt expoſe the Bulk of our Nation unto? Or if God afterwards ſhill reſigne us up unto the pleaſure of any ſingle perſon (when we will have a King like other Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) in his judgment for our preſent diſcontents and grutchings. Are we ſenſible how farte ingratitude on our parts, for bleſſings received may ſeem preparatory for the equity of heavens deciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and re-aſſubiecting us under a pretending Lord, from whom for us to crave ſobriety in adminiſtretion of Juſtice, wil be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted impudence? have we relations parental, filial, uxorions? have we fortunes or tranquilityes privations before our eyes? wee wil certainly confeſſe, as things now ſtand, ſome few acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal inconveniences, or at moſt but temporary, neceſſary taxations. upon our outward creatures, are fitter for an imbrace of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an patience: then a generall hazardous expoſure, of what we already poſſeſſe, unto fortunes, (or rather indeed moral indiſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions) Racket.</p>
               <p>If I have flatter'd my ſelf into theſe preſumptions of advice; or if ignorence or malice can imbody, to undermine the honeſt ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency of my pen, my Iudgement (as a man of green years) may happen to make the offence Bayleable, and the generall ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall of our Iron age, ſhall encourage me, [upon a pious ground no laſſe then morall policy) to a pittiful reſpect of undiſcerning men; while my ſeverer thoughts (by gods help) perſevere in the undoubtedly warrantable conſideration of Gods providence and charity of forgiving mine enemies, whether igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, or envious.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:116271:14"/>
               <head>CHAP. II. Reſpecting Divines.</head>
               <p>FArre from my Abmition it is, to hunt after infamous repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, by oppoſing godly Miniſters, the ready way for Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trifaction of a good name; But I will ſpeak my conſcience and judgement leaſt I be apprehended as unmindful of that noble object of cloquence, Elocution, and reaſon; <hi>Wholeſome Admo, nition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And I muſt heere walke warily, ſome will ſay, leaſt I juſtly contract the juſtice of that Sentence, <hi>It had been better for me to have had a ſtone tyed about my Nec, and therewith imbulg'd to be throwne into the Sea.</hi> So ready are Clergy men, whether <hi>Epiſcopall, Presbyteriall;</hi> or <hi>Independent,</hi> to accompt themſelves Gods ſpecial little ones. But the general diſeaſes of all Churches, ſince there was a Church, changing the Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick from one to another, <hi>viz.</hi> Pride, Ambition, and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs, are as predominant in our Miniſters as ever they were in any ſince Chriſtian Religion was firſt planted in Europ: elſe, to what purpoſe is it, I pray you? Clergy men of the Epiſcopall ſtraine! that you have ſo long, ſo mightily ſtruggled to prove (though weakly God knows) Biſhops divine right, and an indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſible neceſſity of many needleſs formalities in outward ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrations, (extrancous to edification.) Why do you Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians! buſtie ſo vigorouſly to the diſquiet of godly people? and the preſent Civill government, for ſettling of a Claſſical — Presbyterial — and we know nor what — congregationall Church polity, the very high rode to ſubject us Lay-men to more imediate domination then ever, in religious matters? And why laſtly do you (<hi>Independent</hi> Miniſters) exclaime againſt all order? and cannot or will not diſcerne between <hi>Ataxie,</hi> and <hi>Eutexie?</hi> Is it poſſible any thing can be done any duty per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed without ſome Ceremonie? Surely none either morall or ſacred.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:116271:14"/>
               <p>The height and extrem 'tie of paſſions, fluctuating between theſe three, hath rendred all that weare black Coats in ſome meaſure contemptible, and to juſtifie their reſpective quarrells, they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend theſe Three principal grounds obliging.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>The Epiſcopall men pretend a neceſſity of Oathes obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on taken at inſtitution and induction; requiring obedience unto their Ordinarie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>The Presbyterians are imboſted with the Covenant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>The Independent cryes out for liberty of conſcience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the firſt I ſay againe their ordinary, is a <hi>non eus,</hi> wherefore they are at liberty; they cannot: are not bound to hunt after anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nihilations, or ſacrifice themſelves upon an Alter of impoſſibility.</p>
               <p>To the ſecond (not mentioning what poore intereſt of reaſon the Scottiſh Nation had to Covenant with us for a Covenant. in imitation of them, who were not long ſince Feudatory to us, and were never Enfranchiſ'd from their homage by a right Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional conceſſion,) it is I will not ſay a meere Politick, but a convertible Engine good or not ſo good, in qualified and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained ſences: for if we and they ſware to maintaine Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Eccleſiaſtick government, (take it ſo Hypothetically) we did not underſtand what it was, and Doctors of their Church, confeſſe it hath ſuffered much alteration ſince its firſt footing there. If we take it Categorically, admitting they ſware (who took the Covenant) to comply to the Polity moſt agreeable to Gods word we nor they can be our owne judges therein, it is a thing ſo purely ſpirituall. If the Synod could not define which kinde of Church goverment was only imbraceable, their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption will not differ from a venial ſinne (if ſuch ſinnes there be) ſince the putting down of Epiſcopal government, was only lawfull and expedient in order to ſafety of the Nation, that the beſt might be ſet up and men are juſtified as <hi>I</hi> take it by a Vote. That no Church government is of perpetuall divine right, which did wiſely let in ſatisfactory light for the paineful Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wifes of Reformation in all and every reſpective ſunctions and callings.</p>
               <p>To the third, what can be ſaid to be truly conſcience, unleſſe grounded upon Gods word or ſome neceſſarily emaning con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence thereof, otherwiſe (ſay Divines) how eaſily will pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:116271:15"/>apprehenſions reſolve into Error, theſe are to take care they make not torrid miſguided zeal fruitfull in production of ſcuffiers againſt common decencies, withall remembring that the ground and riſe of ſuperſtition, was alwaies zeale, zeal is its parent, time its nurſe, and cunning Preiſts it's Fomentor. Witneſſe, <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But i'le reſume the firſt viz. The Epiſcopall Levites many of whom I confeſſe I honour much for their learning, civility, and breeding, who, were they perhaps well harneſſed, would draw in the Lords yoke gallantly, though as they now ſtand, what miſchiefes, mſeries, affronts, and abuſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> many of theſe will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dact themſelves unto, rather then leave off a Canonical Coat, or a bleſſed Taſſel from their Waſts is wonderful? how vigilant they are to pry into the Vacancy of ſome blind Qratory about Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, or the Country, there with abundant zeal to vent definition doctrine, reaſons and uſe, not miſſing one of theſe rare ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, leaſt they ſhould miſſe of being layd by the heels, and ſo not be celebrated at the next Tavern for Counter Martyrs, where, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving layn three or four dayes or weeks, they get more uſeful lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning then in all their former Academick diſceptations &amp; ayrie di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes; beſides, happily better furniſht, at their egreſſe, with humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity then before, when afflicted with a peice or two in thefr Pock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets.</p>
               <p>Some of theſe Epiſco pall Miniſters are very ignoramuſes and have juſtly becauſe unfit been evicted, yet theſe looking big, will ſpeak with a great deal of formall gravity and are by many extol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led for learned fellowes, whom theſe Black Coats out preſence, with a pontificall kind of deportment. I could never much ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire ſuch men, who can neither ſpeak nor write their ſuppoſed excellencies.</p>
               <p>If they have any thing in them, it is uſeleſſe, yet a man muſt conceipt their reſts ſome mighty, inviſible wonders in their ſculls. And I will heartily confeſſe, this diſtinction J learned from ſome Commanders at Colcheſter Leagure, unto whoſe ſagacity much is by me owed; in order towards right ſcanning of men and intereſts, where J received infinite courteſies from Martiall men inſomuch that (to many good reſpect;) my genius preferreth a lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure far before an univerſity; There was I taught not to adore
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:116271:15"/>black gaberdines, more then gray cloaks, there, mens diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as conquered, conquerours were diſcovered; and I had juſt cauſe to go home with a ſtrong conviction, that there are good Preachers, beſides qualified Miniſters: But this is a digre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſion.</p>
               <p>The good degree of perfonall love I bear to many miniſters of the old ſtamp, wrings truth from me and my ambition would center in ſatisfactions cape, ſo far ſee you love your ſelves, as be. commeth diſcreet men, not biaſſed fot upholding deſpoticall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercſts in Church policy, fervently zealous for promotion of godlineſſe, in its powerfull vivacity remitting ſtate matters to ſtates men; not picking out texts on purpoſe to give ſcandall, believe me, it is a very high ofence for men to make Gods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious word ſeem acceſſary in procreating ſiniſter excurſions. <hi>Chriſt</hi> never preſidented pragmatick invaſions upon publicke magiſtracy ſet over us undeniably by his permiſſive divine providence; which he will not endure to be pieced out with our own.</p>
               <p>No toung of man, or Angels can excuſe you from contracted ſcandall by being wedg'd up, and doting too much upon for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality. <hi>I</hi> ſee no reaſon, why the places in the Old teſtament denoting the Majeſty of the materiall temple, ſhould be ſtrained to elevate the neceſſity of preaching in our Churche, only, for although in Metaphilick reaſoning <hi>ubieties</hi> are explicated with reſpect to bodies, and therefore, if one ask, where Chriſt is? an anſwer is well given, <hi>In heaven he is,</hi> the appoſite anſwer might have been <hi>He ſits at the right hand of his Father:</hi> for, the firſt reſpond. ſcilicet he is in Heaven, doth rather declare unto us his Majeſty, then <hi>ubiety,</hi> for, circumſcriptive or finite <hi>ubiety</hi> falleth not upon him as God, infinite locality or ubiquity (a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine attribute) is competent to God alone, ſpirits have it not; why then are you affraid of private exerciſes in theſe times, by you termed times of perſecution; when as (not deſpiſing reaſonable Order wherein <hi>Room</hi> excells all Churches, though otherwiſe ſhe harh little piety,) your ſelves muſt acknowledg, God is in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very place, in houſes, in Churches, in fields, and what is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: <hi>My houſe is an houſe of Prayer,</hi> muſt be underſtood (as to the term, <hi>Houſe</hi>) in an Allegoricall ſence, that is, <hi>My People
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:116271:16"/>being gathered ſhall pray ſervently, and I will heare them,</hi> the duty is there held forth, not the place prefined to performe the duty in.</p>
               <p>But ſome will by and by object, that I am a ſlender Divine, and unfit to teach or tereat of miſteryes, beware of proud igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, for it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> your vice, who think Laymen unworthy to diſquire or examine Parſons more learned <hi>Axiomes,</hi> the ſpirit of God is not, cannot be concluded in this or that humane qualification, no better expedient for reſtraining from a ſpirit of contradiction, and oppoſition to Publick materiall Churches, then uſeing or them as indiſterent.</p>
               <p>Trouble not your ſelves with Species of Government civill, for if government be but <hi>exercitium Poteſtatis,</hi> no ſcruple need be, but that Texts for obeying Magiſtrates, and that parentall clauſe of the Commandement extending to Governours no leſſe then naturall Parents, may be, without impropriety of reaſon, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood as impoſing ſubſervience to preſent Authority, under which God hath placed us all. Such was due to <hi>Caeſar.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The wiſdome of Superiors is ſuch, I hope, as will eaſily for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give former extravagances, whereunto perhaps a vehement per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, that God would a continuance of things in <hi>Statu quo,</hi> made many of your Coat obnoxious.</p>
               <p>And I think, ſome thing higher, then morall indempnity from want, may reduce the diſcreeteſt Epiſcopall Clergy unto a temperament of ſilent diſſaplauſe, if not condiſcention, unto Heavens pleaſure in alteration of Government, and that is, an hope for liberty to preach Gods word; A felicity (if truely valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) by vaine ſpurning againſt Hornes of Authority, precluded your ſelves and us, who deſire to profit by you? Wherefore the Scope of that gayneable hope (in diſcretion quickly, perponde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating any morall diſlikes in publick tranſactions) will one day (beleeve it) at the great Tribunall be called upon becauſe ſligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly neglected, and oppoſed to all fooliſhly perverſe Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, who becauſe, they may not be ſuffered in their Pulpits med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, with what concernes them not to meddle withall, will render themſelves uncapable to preach at all, interring many times their rich Talents in the Orbes of their owne Braines. <hi>A ſinne againſt the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:116271:16"/>
               <p>Neither are you to doubt, but the State will reunite and fix you (upon compliance) as members of our Corporate body of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> in ſuch a way, as ſhall cancell all reares of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing extraordinary disfavours upon men of former diſaffecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; ſo may all former neceſſary ſeverity uſed towards Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtick perſons be turned into a more ſweet aſpect, whereunto all Subjects are generally invited in the neat, and weighty cloſure of their Declaration of the cauſes moving the Parliament to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the government; whereupon further it will follow, that it may be alſo caſie for ſuch or you (not ſcandalous in life) to be veſted with Cure of Pariſhes wanting able Paſtors, and if it be adjudg'd expedient Tythes be taken away from Eccleſiaſtick perſons, it is probable your intereſts being parochially fixt, will be ſubnixt with proportionate ſhares in any new more equall eſtabliſhment of proviſion for a Godly Miniſtry.</p>
               <p>This counſell will appeare more rationall, when God ſhall give you grace to conſider, that the old Clergy (acting in a perſeverance of contumacions vaine ſtrugling againſt Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) unawares wrackes it ſelſe, upon thoſe ſhelves of miſcheivous rebellion, where from, it hath unthankfully ſweat for deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of others ſeaven or eight years together: for what Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is comparable unto that of rationall creatures againſt reaſons aymiable indictions, againſt that light of morall, and natural preſervation, whoſe radiant luſtre ſhining in our ſoules, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth every man (where Gods glory or Religion come not immediatly into competition) to reſerve himſelfe for Chriſts ſervice, in his due time calling men either as Miniſters, or Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyres?</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>I know it will be quickly replyed what hope is there of true Religions flouriſhing, or increaſe of godlineſſe under this preſent government.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> My Anſwer is (though not well underſtanding where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in true Religion is placed by many men perhaps) experience common of moſt powerful piety free from ſordid formality, and unlimited looſeneſſe pregnant in this Kingdome, may ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly anticipate that needleſſe objection: Many men may be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced of different judgements, touching government civill, yet with a bleſſed harmony together ayming at the fruition of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:116271:17"/>
               <p>But a more immediate eſtoppell wil this following be. <hi>God</hi> in <hi>his eternall preſcience knows well,</hi> what forms of Civill Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations [in order to mens ſinnes clogging reſpective ages of the world] are fitteſt, for making out his own glory, and diſſipa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting thoſe congeſted mountaius of Form, whoſe politick contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances (as to linking of carnall perſonal intereſts, with prentenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of piety) muſt be unraveled, before Chriſts ſecond comming, that al things may alternately ſtoop unto the ſcepter of his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</p>
               <p>The pregnancy of which light is abundant ſatisfaction evin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing thereby unto many diſcreet men, the neceſſity of putting tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional maximes of unqualified or qualified Monarchy in ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or abeyance (as Lawyers call it) of, <hi>I</hi> ſay acquieſcing under preſent Civil Supremacy, becauſe, if there be no acceſſaries in high and loweſt offences, they fear to be made principals in occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally obſtructing Gods deſign (a very high offence) perpetrated ignorantly oftentimes by holy and good men, where, upon a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den dereliction of good ſpirits from them, for their tryals here below, but a little ſpace, they walk darkly under a Carnall Vaile until again rightlie fixt into penitential contemplations, by Gods ſole indulgence.</p>
               <p>Beſides, admitting as ſome would have it, a kind of neceſſity of Kingly Government (an error ſufficiently refuted) for diſpute ſake, ſtraining a morall precept of obedience unto that in an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeciall regard, the conceſsion thereof will inſtantly expire in reaſons boſome; becauſe that laſt mentioned diſpenſation (if a tye unto Monarchy were created by any moral or Judaick pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept (only proper unto Jewes Monarches) is juſt fiable according by way of Letter) where founded upon rules of inevitable neceſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that neceſsity, being cleer, abſolute preſent, certainly yours and all ſubjects caſes in England at preſent, through permiſsive pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence atleaſt, if not conſervative.</p>
               <p>God may yet bring the Epiſcopall Miniſters into a fight of their defections. which with all my ſoul I wiſh, &amp; am drawn into a be, lief, that one reaſon why their prayers hitherto have little prevai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to extricate them from eminent vexations; is; for that they have prayed too much with a limitted love unto themſelves, how
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:116271:17"/>idle and impolitick a ſtratagem your perſwaſions of the People, that certain ſacred Levitical debts are due from lay people, pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able towards Eccleſiaſtick eſtabliſhment, who ſeeth not? the rout can no longer be haltered with groundleſſe terrible feares of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall cenſures; ſo much hath the Apoſtles order for Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication been abuſed to good mens grief, and the great diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of neceſſary order, indeed you may blame your ſelves, if palpable weakneſſes on Miniſters parts have let ordinary capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties underſtand, <hi>the Parſons anger is not as the breath of Gods no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils,</hi> leave off ſupercilious frowns in preaching, time may wear out many inconveniences, no more wholſome way for Epiſcopall Clergy men, then an humble undiſtracted perſeverance, in edifying themſelves, and others in the doctrine of peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence for what's already paſt, (reflecting upon their ſcam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling poſitions about government) and a finall and judicious Reſolution of following the dictates of providence for the future, which I leave to your timeous conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>By this time it may juſtly be expected, <hi>I</hi> ſhould deliver ſome things, as well of diſcovery as admonition, to the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Miniſtry, who (being generally of a <hi>Phariſaicall</hi> temper, ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious of terms of frothy honour) are indeed ſo much the more inexcuſable in their ordinary; defections, by how much they have enjoyed peace, quiet and repoſe (three cardinall ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies unto flatuous <hi>Hypocondriack</hi> paſſions) yet buſtling with reſtleſſe endeavours for impoſition of ſuch an outward Church-policy as may adequate Miniſteriall command, unto Magiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, and make ſtate-policy dependent upon Ecleſiaſtick hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous influence.</p>
               <p>Theſe cry out, <hi>The Army hath deceived them,</hi> nothing ſo for the Souldiery, by qualifying <hi>Presbytery,</hi> and granting mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate faculties unto men of tender Conſciences, hath preſerved them from ſliding into potentiall tyranny over the very ſouls of men.</p>
               <p>The more often <hi>Presbyterians</hi> echo out expoſtulations, againſt Martiall men, that, they have preacht the ſouldiery into a Capacity that but for them, the work could not have gone for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward that, they, in a word are ungratefully dealt withall, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:116271:18"/>a more ſerious black ſcandall, by ſuch ingeminations daily is contracted unto the diſcontented Authors of ſuch carnal reper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſions; for, if they did preach the Souldiery into a capacity, it was either a good work in them, or a bad one: I a good one, their rewards are in Heaven, if indeed never ſo good in it ſelfe, yet, their ends in preaching, might make it bad as to them, they might dream after temporal dominion; <hi>no man ought to do evill</hi> (that is againſt his conſcience) <hi>that good may come thereof.</hi> I dare not charge them with Hypocriſie, Avarice or Ambition, yet if moſt probably men diſcerne the bent of immanent actions, by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral out goings, and it be no ſin for us to judge, where God hath judged before us <hi>O Presbyterian Miniſters.</hi> Your unquenchable deſires of fat Benefices, linking ſome times two or three compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tencies together, removing from place to place; familiarly ſlighting flocks deſtinated unto your charge, ayming at an art in Preaching, are ſhrew'd Symtomes of carnal hearts, of Gods imminent diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure over you; and that it may juſtly be ſuſpected, you are not prefined men for ſetting up inſtrumentally Gods deſigne, in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Reformation.</p>
               <p>The greateſt diſcretion I ever obſerved in you, is, that how ever generally men of plauſible conſciences yet are you al bleſt with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining grace: not a man (for all the great noyſe) that I heare of will venter Sequeſtration for medling with State affaires in Pulpits. I would you would as well leave of private inſtillations into mens heads about the <hi>Covenants</hi> obligation; and againſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary liberty of conſcience, ſince; why we ſhould dance after a Scottiſh Kirk for a government, (when it is notably diſputed whether Chriſt will be pleaſed any formal polity ſhould be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truded on his Saints) no good reaſon can be given, Gods word (as a touch ſtone) being ſubnex'd unto that clauſe in the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. It is a known ſin with <hi>Civilians,</hi> for a man to performe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Oath comporting in tis performance, damage to Religion, Juſtice, and the Common wealth, and I dare appeale unto your owne conſciences, whether your former Doctrines for ſeaven yeares together, did not condemne reſtrictions put upon conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences? whether private exerciſes were not then by you highly magnify'd? whether quenching of the Spirit (which may well be underſtood as in forceing of Conſciences) were not markt out as
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:116271:18"/>an almoſt unexpiable ſin? Laſtly, whether your out cry againſt Tyranicall formes, obtrudable upon conſciences, were reall in thoſe dayes or no? If reall, you are the maine and greateſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectors from juſt principles, if not real, and that ſuch Doctrines were politickly delivered, only out of a ſecret wicked ambition by ſerving times upon hopes (in unhappy conjuncture of affaires) of obteyning Epiſcopal preventions, and fat benefices, thence fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtering clat cularaymes (with your Scottiſh Brethren) gradually to divide with Lay-men, even in diſpoſition of Civil adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: thoſe deſignes were inconſiſtent with Miniſters of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>In ſadneſſe let me tell you (Learned Paſtors) admitting you talk't heartily, and had no ſuch ſiniſter ends, you are at preſent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happily ſubjected unto blame on all hands; how juſtly God knowes, and ſome of your conſciences can well aſſigne reaſons why, God ſhould in juſtice retaliate upon you, that contempt, Presbyterian Miniſters put upon others of the ſame function, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided only from them in opinion about Church government, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the lamentable miſeries of which wretched Epiſcopal men, many of you (to your eternal ſhame be it ſpoken) added a full cup, by ſubſtracting the fift part (allowed by the mercy of the Parliament) from their Wives and Children. O unparalelld cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty! O heathniſh irreligions, Authority knew it not juſt, for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Woemen and Babes to be ruined, for their Fathers hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy extravagances, and our moſt juſt Creator makes it good of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten on Earth, that miſery findes lovers of other mens miſeries out.</p>
               <p>It is no Paradox for me to ſay unto you (ſad Chriſtians) your miſcheife and diſreſpect is from your ſelves. The beſt advice I can give unto the <hi>Pulpit demiſed premiſes,</hi> will be, that for future they would beare ſuch a proportionable reſpect unto other mens conſciences, unto other mens pledge, of Gods love (their Wives and Children) as they deſire Heaven ſhould beare unto them this wil be their beſt mean towards recovery of their loſt reputation, this their principal antidote aganiſt ſcandal; eſpecially in theſe dayes, wherein many ſay (not regarding rules of contraries) there is no ſuch thing as error for, if (ſay they) the greateſt Divines are divided in judgement about matters of faith, the ſtrongeſt Lawyers differ about what is Law, what not, and moſt ſapient
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:116271:19"/>Stateſmen, are plunged in their owne devices; we cannot beleive their is any ſuch thing as eror, becauſe we know not the truth; If no error, no ſinne, what followes? no God, no hell. A ſtrange world we live in, and of theſe wild extravagances in ſinne, which ground ſuch vanities, it ſeems Clergy mens generall inconſtancy arogance ambition and malice are fomentors, whereupon a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Poet taking it ill to be branded with the name of an Athieſt by a Presbyter, hath Satirically deſcanted in this following Rith. micall Poem.</p>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>Satyrus de Caco-presbyteris</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi> Am jam ſubtriſtis increbuit Echo,</l>
                     <l>Dummodo <hi>Presbyter,</hi> egregius praeco.</l>
                     <l>Me dixit <hi>Atheiſmi</hi> totum <hi>Integrale.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Oſtendens ſuo pectore multum in eſſe mali.</l>
                     <l>Sin illud verum ratione facias,</l>
                     <l>Agam tibi <hi>(Sace dotule)</hi> gratias.</l>
                     <l>Contra miraturus cum ſit rumor altus</l>
                     <l>Doctores Synodo evaſiſſe per Saltus</l>
                     <l>Jam dudum: remanes tu <hi>Dulmanus,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Inſulſus Juvenis, at multum ſcurra Canus.</l>
                     <l>Quid te miles odit, ridentque <hi>Generoſi;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Handquaquam cluat eſſe aliquid monſtroſi:</l>
                     <l>Quateuus diu <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e um<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> obstruxiſſe pacem</l>
                     <l>Chriſtianam recte fertur, ac Martis eſſe facem:</l>
                     <l>Qui niſi ſuum polleat <hi>intereſſe</hi> ſtabilire</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Memphitticum,</hi> garrit, <hi>Reformatio non in fieri eſt,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Populumque jugum Chriſti ſaluberrimum</l>
                     <l>Contempſiſſie prave, et expetere terrimum</l>
                     <l>Libertatis Vadum; male <hi>Judependentem</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Chymaeram</hi> adhinire verum minime advertentem.</l>
                     <l>Vah! jam tandem <hi>Laici</hi> didicere verum,</l>
                     <l>Nigra veſtimenta minns eſſe Dei Clerum;</l>
                     <l>Religio cujus eſt ſolummodo formalis,</l>
                     <l>Sit aeque pium <hi>Decimare</hi> quam ludere cum talis.</l>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:116271:19"/>
                     <l>Subridet porro purior Eccleſia Sanctorum,</l>
                     <l>Presbyterum tenere aedhuc ambitum terrenorum,</l>
                     <l>Praeferentem <hi>Evangelio,</hi> ubique <hi>predicabli,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Roſtrum (qua tale) valde quidem amabile</l>
                     <l>Apoſtatieae Stigmate crudeliter percutit</l>
                     <l>Private excercentes, premeditata diffint.</l>
                     <l>Quale docent paſſim <hi>Seraphici</hi> Doctores,</l>
                     <l>Sibique datum Coeli diſtribuere rores.</l>
                     <l>Infra muros ſpiritum impie circumſcribunt</l>
                     <l>Ac vaſtis abdominibus decimas imbibunt.</l>
                     <l>Hi ne Coeli liminis fiunt Clavigeri?</l>
                     <l>Nil minus, <hi>Sathanae</hi> potius Scutigeri.</l>
                     <l>Ergo ne credas (lector] <hi>Omnipotentem</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Hos reformandi velle cauſam contigeutem?</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Heraclitus</hi> ad terras rediens <hi>Cothurnalis.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Rideret ad conspectum Presbyteri parochialis;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Epiſcopatum</hi> verſus dum ſuccuſſaret lipide,</l>
                     <l>Illudque Chriſti regimen predicans intrepide.</l>
                     <l>Cur <hi>Po idorns</hi> olim <hi>Volſoeam</hi> ſit notatus,</l>
                     <l>Quod primus Angliae Sacerdotum graſsabat Sericatus?</l>
                     <l>Volſeos mille dabo, crudelis <hi>Polidorus</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Tantum in Cardinalis vitium ſonorus,</l>
                     <l>Praelati nomen prae Regali poſitio,<note place="margin">Ego &amp; Rex meus.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Lege comparatus, ſibi vix vertetur vitio.</l>
                     <l>Confidunt noſtri quatenus Spurcitijs tentare</l>
                     <l>Duris formalitatibus Chriſtum concatenare.</l>
                     <l>Seeurt nunquam Sancti pia fraude ſatis,</l>
                     <l>Sacerdotibus uſa <hi>Frock-butroniatis.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Quid queſo? none Rumor divino jure niti</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Eccleſiae</hi> nullum Regimen, det medecinam liti?</l>
                     <l>Evincat ſaltem minime Sacerdotes decere,</l>
                     <l>Altercationes ſtrenuas in ſtatu commovere.</l>
                     <l>Compede ſed faederis <hi>Albanici</hi> ligantur</l>
                     <l>Haud <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> conſcientijs mandantur.</l>
                     <l>Sit modo praecox votum modo fides reſcindenda</l>
                     <l>Temere ſuſcepta, ac <hi>Pelinodia</hi> conciuenda.</l>
                     <l>Quis inde regno hactenus extitit necon ior</l>
                     <l>Pateat, Presbyter vel Epiſcopus confidentior,</l>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:116271:20"/>
                     <l>Conſcientias ligari, hi quoque dicunt vitium,</l>
                     <l>Independentes obtrectantes, nec non et <hi>Comitium:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Atqui, ut <hi>Catholice</hi> zelus hic inclaruit,</l>
                     <l>Ad votum ſalubre <hi>Parliamenti</hi> ſubito diſparuit:</l>
                     <l>Hinc miſere confrendunt, neſcientes praedicare;</l>
                     <l>Vetantur quia Plebem titillitio dementare</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Presbiteriali,</hi> ac Species regnandi</l>
                     <l>Rostro definire, <hi>ſub Poena Sequeſtrandi.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Latratus partim lividus confraenatur protinus,</l>
                     <l>Receſſus pertinacia coactus, et ſerotinus.</l>
                     <l>Acceſſit terror <hi>Panicus,</hi> horum livor flacceſcit,</l>
                     <l>Sedantur multo <hi>Malignantes,</hi> Reformatio creſcit,</l>
                     <l>Recente pergant <hi>Ephori</hi> incude collimare</l>
                     <l>Ebullientes Cleri linguas, ſi vellent Regnum ſtare.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If there be any biting truthes in this Poetry or Latin Rithms, Miniſters muſt take in good part (if good they be) for it doth not touch them. As for the ſpiritually proud Miniſter (that white Devil of our age, and diſturber of our quiet,) It matters not three pence, how he underſtandeth them. If the Vanity of Preachers have not diſcompoſ'd this Kingdome much of late, and ruined o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers heretofore, let all men judge. But the piety of ſome humble Church-men, (who have wiſely unfettered themſelves from earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cares, and do quietly preach (in ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon) true ſound Chriſtianity, without mingling State-affairs into their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations, I alwayes judge it neceſſary to heare and imitate; and am very glad even of late the Parliament hath (for the unpreju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicing of many) declared, they will maintaine a Godly diligent Miniſtery; unto whoſe dictates (becauſe men) though we muſt not wholly reſigne up our diſcretions in Religious matters; yet will every quiet ſpirit (for their gifts ſake) give encouragement, and deferre treble reſpect unto them.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:116271:20"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. Reſpecting Lawyers.</head>
               <p>I Am now at laſt come to ſpeak ſome thing unto the Lawy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of <hi>England,</hi> men of mine owne profeſſion; who I know generally will take it ill for any unwinged Gown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, to be pretendedly wiſer then Law. And I alſo (confeſſing my ſelfe a meere Lime or Hackney of the Law) am not much fledg'd with an Apprehenſion, that I can ſpeak halfe ſo much Law as reaſon.</p>
               <p>The Theoretick part of <hi>Englands</hi> Law (though in ſome things defective, in other redundant) I honour, eſpecially for that I beleeve it wiſely diſtributh real inheritance, and uprightly devolves diſcents, whereof alſo Authority hath ſaid they reſolve a permanence, upon former foundations, which deciſion my reaſon teacheth. I do not ſlight or trench upon, when I endeavour a candid repreſentation of errors in Superſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive practice: that muſt of neceſſity challenge from piouſly diſpoſed Governours a timely diſcontinuance, and alteration, where inconveniencies and miſcheifs are Epidemical.</p>
               <p>The great fluttering noiſe as well old practizers in the Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, with Almond Trees on their formal Crownes, as puny Clarks will make, about known <hi>Axiomes, Maximes,</hi> cuſtome, practiſe, and Moth-eaten Records is ſuch, that it hath ſtartled moſt men, deſirous of a more compendious, ſuccinct, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peditious paſſage and deciſion of litigious debates. But I well hope, my contemptible veſſel wil not ſplit upon thoſe lofty, towring Rocks.</p>
               <p>However, this I dare affirme. It is the great miſtery under which our Lawes are Couch't, and the Barbarity of that cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Latine and Norman language, have amuſed many into a ſtrong fancy of the excellency of our proceedings in ſutes.</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:116271:21"/>
               <p>No ſmall wonder it appeareth unto me, men ſhould ſo much dote upon actions of our Anceſtors in times of Popery when (if it be well obſerved) few laws were free from pontificall influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that they cannot ſee the healing of preſent Supremacy is wanting, for reforming things in practiſe Religious, and Civill.</p>
               <p>Tyme, heth drawn a vail, cunning heads have fomented, and Intereſted parties alternatly have fixt a great and ſeemingly good reputation upon erroneous tranſactive practiſes, in actuating the moſt neceſſary and ordinary projects of our Municipiall Law! endleſſe <hi>Maeanders,</hi> length and nicity of pleading formality per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching above equity and ſometimes plain diſtinguiſhable juſtice, have rendred very Law it ſelf odious: whereunto if we ſubioyn, that moſt Juſt captations may be taken againſt proceedings, in our chargeable Chancery, Reaſon will back our aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>Many wiſe men have thought (regarding how a perfection in diſtributive Juſtice is, or ought to be the ſcope of every law) it were proper and convenient for the Subject of England, If the ſame Iudg, at the ſame time (with the Juries conſent) might defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitively correct ſtrictneſſe of law, together with his pronunciati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on directly, where mens poſitive lawes have with all humane poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible care provided againſt probable contingencies, whereby ſome times, a 150 orders might be ſpared both Plaintiff and Defendant and ſutes no more intailed in Chancery from generation to gene ration For, it is an ordinary thing in our Coure of Equity, for a cauſe to ſpin out 8. years before it can come to an hearing.</p>
               <p>Others have quarrelled as much, ſaying that it is leſſe reaſon for law proceedings (if any reaſon at all) to be in <hi>Latine,</hi> then chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery Bils, becauſe of the great danger to a Clyent in miſſing form at Common law. But theſe my great Maſters at law, can, if they pleaſe determine: were not men beſotted to horrible avarice, and Apes to one anothers wickedneſſe.</p>
               <p>Some may ſuppoſe I ſpeak by roat, when I ſhall affirm twenty years are not ſufficient, to learn the practiſe of one Attorney in; ſo full of variety is law practice, and indeed head Officers in Courts make it upon the matter what they pleaſe, no vivacity of wit can reach the Vanity of Formes in reaſonable time, theſe
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:116271:21"/>Myſteties make the Subject more miſerable (truly we may ſay it) then thoſe Nations whoſe lawes are unwritten, For, upon the nicetyes and intricacies of Headings are hatcht demurrers,<note place="margin">See Baſili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron lac. Regis pag. 90 lib 2.</note> a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice meerly to ſpin out money and tyme, ſuch exceptions being moſtwhat taken to formal defects, not materiall, and though the parties meaning be evident, a miſplaced word or miſtaken ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence ſhall cancel all done before.</p>
               <p>Men of ſlendreſt capacityes diſcern, how much plaintiffs are favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in our Courts. And ſtrangers admire at the Multitudes of Men depending upon legall matters here in <hi>England</hi> I beleive there are at leaſt ten and ten thouſand qualifyed Officers at law in England, reckoning upon a true accompt, beſide running ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citors infinite, this moſt ſuperfluous brood (maintained only by proſit ariſing by Law) is generated not through defect in the fun damentall part of our law, neither doth it require ſuch Multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious managery, were the wayes and means tending unto the iuſt ends of law explained ſmoothed made right and ſhortned; for prevention of which ambages, and circuit in actions theſe two rules are very (in my poor judgment) expedient as a prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratory to more.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>That the generall Iſsue, be pleaded in all acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>That good Coſts be Ordered upon unjuſt Sutes. and Iudgement for them preſently awarded.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>The Attorney will inſtantly cry out. What then ſhall become of all our Preſident Books? if the generall iſſue be pleaded? It were very hard if a People ſhould generally ſuffer for feare they ſhould make their preſidents uſeleſſe.</p>
               <p>The like will Counſellors alleage, when thouſands of Fees in a terme ſhall be ſaved by Generall Pleas.</p>
               <p>Thus (lawyers) you ſeek a preſervation of your owne Intereſt in the diſtemper of our whole Nation.</p>
               <p>As the Caſe now ſtands, he that hath the weightieſt purſe many times carryes away the Bell, right or wrong. for any man may bring Error upon Error, even in perſonal Actions, and men are tyred out with ſeeking for their owne.</p>
               <p>A man may outlaw his Neighbour for a cauſe, or without a
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:116271:22"/>cauſe: the remedy againſt the Sheriffe is troubleſome, and moſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what, worſe then the diſeaſe: the grounds of theſe proceedings I know, but they are damnably abuſed: Sheriff, cry out as much againſt Chequer mens abuſes not without reaſon.</p>
               <p>No unintereſted man can plead for continuance of theſe, and forty worſe inconveniences, which may in due time be repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Attorneyes would get more mony, I am ſure more honeſtly, if practice were contracted: for as things are, needleſſe, lazie, ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Officers, Monopolize making up a proceſſe, and tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Attorneys lay out their mony (getting it againe with curſes in the Country) while trudging up and down they can get (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides cutting and making, or ſharpning good hand-bills) but ten groats a Term. In ſo much, that it is now as eſſentially neceſſary for an Attorney, to be a good foot-man; as not to have a ſoft place in the hinder part of his head.</p>
               <p>And who will not ſtand amazed, that is not a corrupt Lawyer., when it ſhall be truly told him the myſtery of an Attorneys trade is greater then that of a Counſellor? That the ſmalleſt actions tryall will coſt at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> ſix or ſeven pounds (where ſhall a poore man have it?) That men muſt pay Fines for liberty to enter Actions by originall writ? that money muſt be paid in the pound for damage laid, and damage cleere? that one Court never gives leſſe then forty ſhillings coſts upon judgements by default, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, the other ſeldome more (but when finable) then Twenty. That <hi>Allegories</hi> are ordinary in Law ſuggeſtions, both in cancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larian and legall proceedings. That by laying an Imaginarie <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuatus,</hi> a man may bring an action for a ſhilling in the Courts at <hi>Weſtminster?</hi> That the ſame coſts are given where the Damage to the Plaintiffe appears not to have five ſhillings as where the Plaintiffes prejudice was forty times, as conſiderable? That, a petty legall Tyranny is howerly exerciſed by forreyne North, and We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern Attorneyes, by reaſon of the diſtance of the places from <hi>London.</hi> But time will not permit, let theſe hints ſuffice at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, till more leiſure, to remonſtrate, how neceſſary Law Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation is, and how farre from an happy and well ordered Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity <hi>Englands</hi> Adminiſtration is, till theſe things be reduced into order, and pragmatick buſie Lawyers, whether qualified or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualified,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:116271:22"/>be reſtrained from taking advantage of theſe laxations in the practick managerie of Law. Authority cannot do all at once: wiſe men know every Commonwealth is judged by what is commonly and ordinarily done; and it is a very hard thing to prove Common Barretors. Is there any man ſo ſenceleſſe to think it a ſin, that either that Law againſt them, or any other Law humane be corrected, uſage is an Aſſe, when time comes in, umpire of practiſe, Lawes are cancelled, when obſolete, or noxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, ſoft, or cruell, diſconſtitutionall, or idle for a people; when organically they are imperfect, and ſelfe Miniſters accidentally (though good) of bad manners.</p>
               <p>In order whereunto to make out my aſſertion domeſtically: leſt I ſhould ſeem to owe more unto the nimble wits of theſe days, then unto that great reaſon (without vanity be it ſpoken) I am able to bring for tranſlating our Lawes into the Engliſh tongue. I will here declare my well wiſhes, that it might not any longer be lockt up in an unknowne Barbariſme, or impectorated with a few.</p>
               <p>The dangers conting ible in poſſibilty muſt be rare by it's Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing, the advantages very conſiderable, when (being reduced from her looſe expatiated volumes under Alphabetick diviſions) ſhee ſhall wed an Engliſh Government of ſimple luſtre.</p>
               <p>This is the way to put her into a capacity of winning her cauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Enemies unto obedience of her juſt ſanctions; ſhe will then, more cleerely evidence (being a little reformed by competent hands) it was ever and is ſtill in part, her Midwives either neſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, corruption, or retchleſſeneſſe, which hath hitherto cauſed many of her Children to grow Ricketty. In her the cauſe is not, <hi>yet are not her gray haires ſignes of perfect wiſdome:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Men talke of morall Equity, right, Fredome from Ty<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ranicall uſage; I dare maintaine it, untill every one, as an Engliſh man, may freely read his duty in Engliſh, and look into that which muſt regulate his deportment, and intereſt Civill (not repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table by Statutes) and thereby diſcerne the neceſſity of ſome times admitting particular miſchiefs, rather then generall inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences: Vaine have been, ever will be all arguments or pretenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preferring reſpective diſcretion of precedent, preſent, or fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:116271:23"/>Law-givers. Thus may the Reaſon of Law be cleared; and upon what grounds, prudence and reſpect unto morall equity, of Iudaick lawes, lawes of England are founded.</p>
               <p>Neither is it ever expectable vulgar heads can be reduced from generall prejudice againſt our Lawes, while they are looked upon as inconſiderable or unfit objects of Pitty; and no expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent laide, for their ſatisfaction in their juſt Cavill againſt Law language, that Relick and badge of our <hi>Norman</hi> ſlavery.</p>
               <p>I can admit the current of that Objection, <hi>viz</hi> That ordinary men will not be much wiſer for it's tranſlation: But certainly it is impertinent, for they will be better ſatisfyed, if not with the reaſon of the Law (becauſe perhaps they cannot reach it) yet will this Cordial refocillate their ſpirits, becauſe then, it ſhall lye in their owne Powers to be their owne Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors.</p>
               <p>Beſides, it may be well ſuppoſed upon Engliſhing of it, the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple will not ſo much murmur and repine at Iudgments, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſions given in Courts of Juſtice: When as all along both plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiffe and Defendant may track with much facility thoſe paths, wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer heads have chalked out for preſervation of Common right, and reciprocal Iuſtice between partyes.</p>
               <p>They are miſtaken who ſay ignorance is the Nurſe of Civil de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion. Engliſhmen naturally diſguſt or ſlight things placed above them. Every man is not bred a Scholer, or book earned, what if the Maſes have been favourable un to him? im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments of many men will not afford them time for ſtuddying the craggy Language of our law, upon this ignorance is an Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demick vice.</p>
               <p>And yet I have not known more unhappy men in ſutes, then mere Scholers, for they looking upon generall rules of Equity only, can hardly be drawn (till they are well ſmarted for their Scholaſtick preſumptions) into a belief of the wholſome compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of our Lawes fitted in their poſition, aſwel unto adequate reaſon of naturall right, as appropriated moſt part unto the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutional bent of our Nation: upon this anvill of cauſeleſſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content and prejudice it is true, occaſion is improperly taken and Miniſters heartily threaten Attorneys, as brambles in the State, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:116271:23"/>our bills are neither by them intelligible nor legible, in that, they are unreaſonable.</p>
               <p>All arts have their forms, termes. Lawyers theirs. It is ſaid a Parſon lately preacht this doctrine. That his pariſhioners ought to obſerve, <hi>Court hand was an Idoll, and God would daſh Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers for all their daſhes,</hi> But at ſuch we ſmile,</p>
               <p>As violent on the other hand are Councellors, and moſt attor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys againſt all military men, who dare ſpeak plain Engliſh, and petition for Reformation in Law practice. Theſe men conſider not, being wedg'd up with preſent forms, how moſt of our lawes in England had military grounds for their begetting. And thus much my Diſcretion teacheth me, to affirm impartially; Many of the Governing part of the preſent Army, are bleſt with extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Reaſon, far beyond moſt of our learnedeſt Ply-baggs. It matters not from whom our help floweth if we get cure of civill Diſtempers, and from their indeavours it is moſt likely to proceed If <hi>I</hi> miſtake not.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> perceive that a ſtrong fancy peſſeſſeth moſt Lawyers of a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary ſingle Governor, whom they alwaies (vainly enough) loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked upon in his politick Capacity as an immortall Deity. But that is a meer fiction, like the houſes in aſtrology.</p>
               <p>I deſire to be reſolved how a parliament could order the ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the crown of England from <hi>Hen</hi> 6. to <hi>Edw.</hi> the 4th. up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on breach of a Condition; if a condition be an Hereditament. <hi>Henry</hi> the 6th was in by diſcent from <hi>Hen.</hi> the 5th, <hi>Edw.</hi> the 4ths entry was tolled, yet (by that Parliament at the end of <hi>H.</hi> the 6th. raign and beginning of <hi>E.</hi> 4th. judged lawfull, where was the King in the intervall of <hi>H.</hi> and <hi>E?</hi> Theſe are bables for a man to think upon ſeriouſly, for that paradox of the immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Kings and Biſhops here, is actually reſolved to annihila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>All States and Potentates are taught by natural reaſon to ingage their ſubjects into obedience.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The preſent new engagement</hi> muſt not be judged any innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or cruell Obtruſion, but rather a carefull indulgence for ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the whole, complecting every mans exactible duty, leſt any ſhould pretend ignorance of that duty, for actuating whereof, to
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:116271:24"/>wholeſome ends, hee is deſigned. This every man will beleeve convenient, whoſe Braines are not diſturbed with the <hi>QVEEN OF WATERS</hi> influence; and our immediate rivolets of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous honor, need not much complaine or curſe their fates, <hi>FOR BEING SVBIECTED TO THE LAW;</hi> ſince upon their owne ſtock of exhalations, reſhowred downe, they for a time ſurvived their fountaine; and may yet runne a more direct courſe in another Region, if they pleaſe, or can ſtoop to Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</p>
               <p>Neither hath the Common Lawyer above all men, any cauſe to repine at preſent fixing of our State, for that his craft or my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery is preſerved intine, his rode toward ſubſiſtence the ſame, only it may ſeeme reaſonable, in lieu of that felicity, he ſhould rightly valew it, and informe where Reformation of abuſes is moſt wanting.</p>
               <p>For mine owne part, having (with a good intention) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed theſe papers: I muſt begg leave in one word, by way of preventing prejudice, to Apologize, leſt my advice herein gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, or any repreſentation obvious unto my ſcope, ſhould be unworthily apprehended as ſavouring either of pride, baſe ends, or partiallity: for what ever I have written to thoſe three fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned qualifications of Gentlemen, <hi>Divines,</hi> or Lawyers, my requeſt is, ſhould be underſtood, as an efflux upon exigence of Method propoſed: not that I any way undervalue others, whether Merchants, Tradeſmen, Mechanicks or Yeomen, nay not the more low ſort of men, becauſe to my ſence, every reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pective part of theſe are equally as conſiderably uſefull in our Common wealth, and it is civility makes a Gentleman deboyſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe a Clown, and ſonne of the earth, my Prayer unto God ſhall be, that all men (ſetting aſide frothy Titles) would cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their ambitions in him, who is alone able to reduce certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, peace and reſt in this unſetled humorous age: an acquieſcence in his providence will diſpell Melancholick perturbations: when all Phyſick beſides muſt prey a little upon the naturall Spirits of the Body, that will compoſe the Soule, and ſet the tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moyled creature free from all poſſibility of miſeries, dangers, and feares. As for the Species of Magiſtracie (in its abſtracted
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:116271:24"/>eſſence with Heaven in variable) yet as to men alterable in all ages, the leſſe private perſons unhinge their braines in conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of it. certainly their night reſts will be more quiet— But,</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Caelum ipſum petimus ſtultitia, neque</l>
                     <l>Iracunda Jovem ponere fulmina patimur.<bibl>
                           <hi>Horat,</hi>
                        </bibl>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Wee ſhoot at Starres, and vainly ayme to ſtop</l>
                     <l>Iove's Thunderbolt, as 'tis about to drop.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>Such is the preſumption of this age, that men ſin adviſedly in ſwallowing up generall freedomes by ſpeciall intereſts; ſome are as prepoſterous in hurrying the wheels of Reformation to faſt downe hill, dangering the very Axell-tree of its whole car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riadge, as others are to Curious in avoydance of ſhallow rakes, wherein ſhe cannot ſink deep; others ſay a Sledge without wheels may ſerve a Lady of her condition that will (they think) convey her from Conſtable unto Conſtable well enough, and time enough for any neceſſity, or haſte there is of her pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe.</p>
               <p>The honeſt well affected Country man who thinks all things can, or ſhould be perfected with one Swap, now the King is gone, may ſeem to be the firſt, with whoſe not well guided rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, perhaps a few diſcontented private perſons among'ſt our Armie may jump alſo.</p>
               <p>Next thoſe, will follow the temperate meere Divine in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond reſemblance, and as ſubſervient unto him, a Brace of his beſt Pariſhioners (commonly old Gentlemen; good huntſ-men) theſe could be content with a Reformation, But are afraid of her looks, and neceſſary attendance.</p>
               <p>Into the laſt reſemblance, Lawyers muſt moſt properly be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacted Analogically, ours is, ſay they, a profeſſion, and it can be no ſin for a man to follow his calling: But I feare, to take iſſue with Heaven upon a diſpute, that for the maintenance of their families, and for avoyding the Caracter of one of <hi>Pauls Infidells</hi> in not providing for our charges, we traced corrupt practices, will at Gods tribunall, prove a very ſleeveleſſe allegation, when <hi>Madam</hi> Juſtice ſhall file in Heavens moſt Chriſtian Court, a
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:116271:25"/>provocation againſt <hi>fac ſimile</hi> Clerks, where I ſay, quaint pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations by way of excluſion, ſhall not hinder taking iſſue upon the whole matter, no Juriſdictions of a Court incapacitated can be pleaded; no errors alligned afterwards, in a word no eſſoign nor imparlence can be admitted. While we perſevere in ſcrewing rigor of general lawes, up to the height of injury, we are a burden unto our fellow Subjects, we weaken the eſteem of the common-lawes wholeſome conſtitution, and mainly ſuffocate poſſibilities of felicities attingible by the publick, we hand Reformation from one to another, bewilder our ſelvs, and hazard our future ſafety.</p>
               <p>But integrity is the beſt policy, and as a Lawyer lately upon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother occaſion did affirm: That al the lawyers in England could not make one caſe law, which was not reaſon: ſo let us uani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moufly pray our practiſe may be regulated in its exorbitances by reaſon, and vindicated from thoſe many juſt aſperſions it groaneth under, <hi>leaſt though the bread of deceit be ſweet our mouths may afterwards be gravelled.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For preſent, My thoughts are no longer mine own. This corolla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry caution I ſhall leave unto all ſober men of the three qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions prereflected upon, That they would well conſider how dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous a New Repreſentative may prove, till</hi> Ireland <hi>be fully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, and people fixt into a better ſence of their Duty: regarding that no wiſe Neighbouring Nations will commend in us, a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>impowring experienced men from winding up their long labours into a Bottom, whoſe honors, lives, and fortunes are reciprocally involved in the extreme diffuſion of Policy for generall ſafety: It is our defection from preſent Patriots all diſcontented parties at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, as their laſt and ſecret ſtratagem for our further diſquiet; which ſad conſequence, after ſo vaſt expence of blood</hi> and <hi>treaſure may concern every diſcerning ſpirit to deprecate.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:116271:25"/>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
